<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<document>
  <properties>
    <title>FAQ</title>
    <author email="lmike@dev.java.net">Liaw Mike Djoesman</author>
    <author email="mister__m@dev.java.net">Michael Nascimento Santos</author>
  </properties>
  <body>
    <section name="FAQ">
      <p>Frequent questions:
      <ul>
        <li><a href="#Is it possible to create a web application using genesis?">
        Is it possible to create a web application using genesis?</a></li>
        <li><a href="#How does genesis compare with Spring?">
        How does genesis compare with Spring?</a></li>
        <li><a href="#When will genesis support swing api?">
        When will genesis support swing api?</a></li>
        <li><a href="#How can I use genesis within J2ME applications?">
        How can I use genesis within J2ME applications?</a></li>
        <li><a href="#Why am I getting a NullPointerException in a getSession()
        call?">Why am I getting a <code>NullPointerException</code> in a 
        <code>getSession()</code> call??
        </a></li>
        <li><a href="#Where is technical support?">Where is technical support?
        </a></li>
      </ul>
      </p>
      <subsection name="Is it possible to create a web application using genesis?">
        <p>genesis current version can already be used with any web framework,
        such as Struts or WebWork.</p>
        <p>In order to create a web application, it's just necessary to create
        a project that uses genesis business components. Besides that, genesis
        will have its own web framework, but right now, it is not true.</p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection name="How does genesis compare with Spring?">
        <p>These two projects have different goals. While genesis focus in 
        resolving the problem of providing an easier way to develop  graphical 
        interface and business code, Spring framework focus in getting J2EE
        development easier and in promoting the use of certains practices, like
        reducing the cost of programming to interfaces programming. 
        Although both frameworks support Hibernate, Spring has a more generic 
        dependency injection and genesis has also a generic one but not 
        so complete as the Spring one. However, some 
        genesis functionalities are not provided by Spring, such as <a href=
        "ui_additional_features.html#Working_with_dynamic_searches">Working 
        with dynamic searches</a>.</p>
        <p>Generic support to dynamic searches should be added to genesis
        release 0.3</p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection name="When will genesis support swing api?">
        <p>Swing will be supported in nexts genesis releases. There is no
        certain date for this to happen, but mostly it will be done till mid
        year.</p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection name="How can I use genesis within J2ME applications?">
        <p>It is recommended to only use a sub-set of the functionalities
        provided in the package UI, like the direct use of <code>
        net.java.dev.genesis.ui.thinlet.BaseThinlet</code> for example.
        Advanced functionalities like binding will mostly not work within
        those environments.</p>
        <p>To support all major genesis functionalities within J2ME is part
        of the genesis development team, but there is no certain date for this
        to happen.</p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection name="Why am I getting a NullPointerException in a getSession()
        call?">
        <p>There are several situations where this problem might occur. 
        Basicaly they are:
        <ul>
          <li>The class that depends on the injection of the <code>
          Session</code> is in the wrong place within the source code hierarchy
          (in the client module, for example). This way, the weaving process
          will not affect that class as intended and the Hibernate session
          will not be injected.</li>
          <li>There has been a method call chain using business objects.
          In this case, a Hibernate <code>Session</code> is not injected
          in secondary calls. To fix this code, one just needs to use
          the <code>setSession(Session)</code> method of the callee object
          using the caller <code>Session</code> as parameter.</li>
          <li>In the case it is first time one is trying to build a new 
          project, build process may not be working properly.</li>
        </ul>
        </p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection name="Where is technical support?">
        <p>Regular and free support can be found through project <a
        href="../mail-lists.html">discussion lists</a>.</p>
        <p>In case further support is required like architecture definition,
        perfomance improvement, genesis training or related technologies
        training, Summa Technologies may be contacted as bellow:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Summa Technologies:
            <ul>
              <li>Address: US Steel Tower, 53rd Floor - 600 Grant Street -
              Pittsburgh, PA 15219</li>
              <li>phone: +01.412.258.3300</li>
              <li>Fax: +01.412.258.3299</li>
              <li><a href="mailto:info@summa-tech.com">info@summa-tech.com</a></li>
            </ul>
          </li>
          <li>Summa Technologies do Brasil:
            <ul>
              <li>Address: Rua Funchal, 411 - 11o. andar, CJ. 112 - São
              Paulo - 04551-060</li>
              <li>Phone: +55.11.3846.1622</li>
              <li>Fax: +55.11.3845.3514</li>
              <li><a href="mailto:brazil@summa-tech.com">brazil@summa-tech.com</a></li>
            </ul>
          </li>
        </ul>
      </subsection>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>