<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<document>
  <properties>
    <title>FAQ</title>
    <author email="lmike@dev.java.net">Liaw Mike Djoesman</author>
    <author email="mister__m@dev.java.net">Michael Nascimento Santos</author>
  </properties>
  <body>
    <section name="FAQ">
      <p>Frequent questions:
      <ul>
        <li><a href="#Is it possible to use genesis to build a web application?">Is
        it possible to use genesis to build a web application?</a></li>
        <li><a href="#How does genesis compare to Spring?">
        How does genesis compare to Spring?</a></li>
        <li><a href="#When will genesis provide SWT support?">
        When will genesis provide SWT support?</a></li>
        <li><a href="#How can I use genesis in J2ME applications?">
        How can I use genesis in J2ME applications?</a></li>
        <li><a href="#Why am I getting a NullPointerException in a getSession()
        call?">Why am I getting a <code>NullPointerException</code> in a
        <code>getSession()</code> call??
        </a></li>
        <li><a href="#How can I get technical support?">How can I get technical
        support?</a></li>
      </ul>
      </p>
      <subsection name="Is it possible to use genesis to build a web application?">
        <p>The current genesis release can already be used with any web
        framework, such as Struts or WebWork.</p>
        <p>In order to create a web application, the only thing needed is to
        create a project that uses genesis business components. There are plans
        for building a web framework for genesis itself, but they have not been
        implemented so far.</p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection name="How does genesis compare to Spring?">
        <p>These two projects have different goals. While genesis focuses in
        resolving the problem of providing an easier way to develop graphical
        interfaces and business code, the Spring framework focuses in make J2EE
        development easier and in promoting the use of certains practices, like
        programming to interfaces. Although both frameworks support Hibernate,
        for example, Spring has a more generic dependency injection mechanism
        while genesis has a generic one that is not so generic. However, some
        genesis functionalities are not provided by Spring, such as <a href=
        "paging_and_dynamic_search.html#Dynamic_criteria_searching">support for
        dynamic searches</a>.</p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection name="When will genesis provide SWT support?">
        <p>SWT will be supported in next release. Maybe, in a month.</p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection name="How can I use genesis in J2ME applications?">
        <p>It is recommended to only use a sub-set of the functionalities
        provided in the UI package, such as the direct use of <code>
        net.java.dev.genesis.ui.thinlet.BaseThinlet</code> for example.
        Advanced functionalities like binding will mostly not work within
        those environments.</p>
        <p>To support all major genesis functionalities within J2ME is part
        of the genesis development team plans, but there is no certain date
        for this to happen.</p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection name="Why am I getting a NullPointerException in a getSession()
        call?">
        <p>There are several situations that cause this problem to occur.
        Basically they are:
        <ul>
          <li>The class that depends on the injection of the
          <code>Session</code> instance is in the wrong place within the
          source code hierarchy (in the client module, for example). This way,
          the weaving process will not affect that class as intended and the
          Hibernate session will not be injected.</li>
          <li>There has been a method call chain using business objects.
          In this case, a Hibernate <code>Session</code> is not injected
          in secondary calls. To fix this, one just needs to use
          the <code>setSession(Session)</code> method of the callee object
          using the caller <code>Session</code> instance as parameter.</li>
          <li>In case it is first time one is trying to build a new
          project, the build process may not be working properly.</li>
          <li>The method hasn't been properly annotated with @Remotable, 
          @Transactional or @Criteria</li>
        </ul>
        </p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection name="How can I get technical support?">
        <p>Free basic support can be obtained in the project <a
        href="../mail-lists.html">discussion lists</a>.</p>
        <p>If further support is required, like architecture definition,
        perfomance improvements, genesis or related technologies training,
        Summa Technologies may be contacted in the following locations:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Summa Technologies:
            <ul>
              <li>Address: US Steel Tower, 53rd Floor - 600 Grant Street -
              Pittsburgh, PA 15219</li>
              <li>phone: +01.412.258.3300</li>
              <li>Fax: +01.412.258.3299</li>
              <li><a href="mailto:info@summa-tech.com">info@summa-tech.com</a></li>
            </ul>
          </li>
          <li>Summa Technologies do Brasil:
            <ul>
              <li>Address: Rua Funchal, 411 - 11o. andar, CJ. 112 - São
              Paulo - 04551-060</li>
              <li>Phone: +55.11.3846.1622</li>
              <li>Fax: +55.11.3845.3514</li>
              <li><a href="mailto:brazil@summa-tech.com">brazil@summa-tech.com</a></li>
            </ul>
          </li>
        </ul>
      </subsection>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>