<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<document>
  <properties>
    <title>genesis</title>
    <author email="allanjones@dev.java.net">Allan Jones Batista de Castro</author>
    <author email="mister__m@dev.java.net">Michael Nascimento Santos</author>
    <author email="pmadril@uol.com.br">Pablo Jorge Madril</author>
  </properties>
  <body>
    <section name="genesis">
       <p><font size="+1"><a 
       href="https://genesis.dev.java.net/servlets/ProjectDocumentList?folderID=7588&amp;expandFolder=7588&amp;filter=genesis-all">Quick 
       Download</a></font></p>
    </section>
    <section name="Overview">
      <p>genesis is an open-source framework that aims to bring simplicity and
      productivity to enterprise application development, ensuring scalability, 
      robustness and testability of your software. The main goal is to simplify 
      the development of business components and the construction of complex 
      graphical interfaces with minimum effort for developers. To accomplish its 
      mission, genesis combines several open-source frameworks in a completely 
      transparent way for developers, through the use of AOP (Aspect Oriented 
      Programming). Our main challenge is to allow people with little knowledge 
      of the Java platform to develop robust applications fast, without 
      requiring them to learn several new technologies and complex concepts. We 
      invite you to experience our approach to the problem.</p>
    </section>
    <section name="How to start?">
      <subsection name="Developers">
         <p>Download genesis and read the <a 
         href="documentation_intro.html">User manual</a>. Run the <a 
         href="useradmin_sample.html">samples</a> and start developing using the
         <a href="empty_project.html">ready-to-use project structure</a>. 
         You will be creating your own applications in a short period. If you 
         have any questions, read our <a href="faq.html">FAQ</a> and join 
         our mailing list. To subscribe to our mailing list, just send an e-mail 
         to <a 
         href="mailto:users-subscribe@genesis.dev.java.net">users-subscribe@genesis.dev.java.net</a>.
         Then, just reply to the confirmation e-mail sent by the server. To send 
         any messages to our list, write to <a 
         href="mailto:users@genesis.dev.java.net">users@genesis.dev.java.net</a>.
         </p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection name="Framework Developers">
         <p>To understand genesis architecture better, please refer to the
         <a href="advanced_introduction.html">advanced documentation</a>. Find 
         out details about technologies used by the framework (AOP, IoC, 
         etc).</p>
      </subsection>
    </section>
    <section name="Questions?">
       <subsection name="Mailing Lists">
       Subscribe to our <a 
       href="mailto:users-subscribe@genesis.dev.java.net">mailing list</a> and 
       have your questions answered by the genesis core team.
       </subsection>
       <subsection name="FAQ">
       Frequently asked questions are answered <a href="faq.html">here</a>
       </subsection>
    </section>
 </body>
</document>