<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<document>
  <properties>
    <title>XDoclet extensions</title>
    <author email="mister__m@dev.java.net">Michael Nascimento Santos</author>
  </properties>
  <body>
    <section name="XDoclet extensions">
      <p><a href="http://xdoclet.sourceforge.net/">XDoclet</a> is a framework that
      makes it possible to generate code from special Javadoc tags present in
      source code. genesis' development started when the most recent XDoclet
      version available was 1.2.0 and several resources were still not part of
      it, especially when it came to its Hibernate integration.</p>
      <p>To work around those limitations, genesis' distribution contained some
      modified XDoclet modules for a while. As XDoclet itself evolved, some
      new features eventually became part of it, but the way the extensions
      present in genesis were being distributed prevented features from the
      overridden modules to be used - both from the validation and hibernate
      modules. Since genesis 2.2, this distribution has been modified so it is
      easier to use both features that are part of the original XDoclet as well
      as the ones made available by genesis.</p>
      <p>The current version of the extensions contains all features that are
      part of XDoclet 1.2.2 and some modifications as explained below.</p>
    </section>
    <section name="genesis module">
      <p><a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/commons/validator/">Commons
      Validator</a> was originally part of <a
      href="http://struts.apache.org">Struts</a> and that is why the support
      provided by XDoclet is limited to using Commons Validator with this web
      framework. That is the reason tags that generate the Commons Validator
      xml file are prefixed by <code>@struts.</code> and have an explicit
      dependency on Struts classes.</p>
      <p>The XDoclet extension module named genesis provides tags with the same
      semantics as the <code>@struts.validator*</code> tags, except the tags'
      names begin with <code>@genesis.validator</code> and they work with POJOs
      instead of requiring the annotated classes to extend a Struts class. An
      example of how to use these tags can be found in the <a
      href="validating_data.html">documentation about
      validation support</a>.</p>
    </section>
    <section name="hibernate module">
      <p>The hibernate module supports some new features that are not available
      in the original module bundled with XDoclet. The main ones are support
      for generating the <code>meta</code> element by using the
      <code>@hibernate.meta</code> tag, definition of many-to-one relationships
      with tables with composite keys, external queries merging and also
      component mapping merging. For more infomation, please refer to the <a
      href="http://opensource.atlassian.com/projects/xdoclet/browse/XDT-1312">issue</a>
      submitted to the XDoclet project that describes the changes made by the
      genesis team.</p>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>